<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[James Burke]]></title>
    <link href="http://jrburke.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://jrburke.com/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T23:06:36.343Z</updated>
    <id>http://jrburke.com/</id>
    <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Burke]]></name>
    </author>

    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Blog]]></title>
        <link href="http://jrburke.com/2012/09/05/new-blog/"/>
        <updated>2012-09-05T23:06:36.343Z</updated>
        <id>http://jrburke.com/2012/09/05/new-blog/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will do new posts from this site, <a href="http://jrburke.com/">jrburke.com</a>. There is
a feed link in the header if you want to track this site in an feed reader.</p>

<p>I was using <a href="http://tagneto.blogspot.com">tagneto.blogspot.com</a>, but
I have wanted something different for a while now.</p>

<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>

<ul>
<li>Write posts in Markdown. There is too many weird transforms when
using the "rich text" control in Blogger.</li>
<li>Better display of inlined code.</li>
<li>More control over the site.</li>
</ul>

<p>I was using Blogger because I do not like the idea of server administration. I
want to spend my time on solving code problems, not on computer bookkeeping.</p>

<h2 id="requirements">Requirements</h2>

<h3 id="basic">Basic</h3>

<p>My needs for a blog are very modest. I do not need image galleries. I want
to be able to write text, and to show code. I do not want to run a server to
dynamically generate content. This implies running a server API service at the
minimum, and then worrying about more bookkeeping. I'm fine doing the code
generation locally and uploading static content to the server.</p>

<h3 id="javascripttooling">JavaScript tooling</h3>

<p>I considered using something like <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, but I find
having to manage Ruby and installing gems disheartening (see above about
bookeeping). This is not a knock against Ruby in particular, I have the same
sinking feeling when using Python. I like how node programs default to "local
install" layouts, and I am much more fluent in JavaScript.</p>

<h3 id="javascriptnotrequiredinbrowser">JavaScript not required in browser</h3>

<p>Most of my time is spent is thinking about web apps that need JavaScript, and I
really like using JavaScript. However, for plain content, I just want to use
JavaScript for enhancements. If the JavaScript fails to load, then the content
should still be reachable and readable.</p>

<p>I also do not want to load a bunch of JavaScript for "social sharing". Making sharing
easier is the responsibility of browser chrome/UI. The browser is my "user agent".</p>

<p>I also do not like supporting business models that encourage
tracking people across web sites. It is a valid way to support a
business, and I may even work on applications that use it as a way to pay their
costs, but this is my personal space, and I can afford to be a jerk about it here.</p>

<p>I got close to not needing any JavaScript, but ended up using it to load some fonts from
<a href="https://typekit.com/">TypeKit</a>, and for using <a href="http://prismjs.com/">Prism</a> for
making pretty code samples. However, if they fail to load,
the content can still be read.</p>

<p>While TypeKit does some tracking, I am fine with it since it is about paying
font designers for their work, and I want to feel pretty. Or at the very least,
I want the site to look pretty.</p>

<h3 id="comments">Comments</h3>

<p>The static generation approach makes it difficult to deal with comments. I am
wary of comments in general. I appreciate getting feedback, but I want it
focused and on-topic. I also do not believe my posting area is a place
where people should have the right to comment. They should create their own
spaces for that.</p>

<p>The comment system should not allow anonymous comments. It is important for
the type of online discourse that I mostly do -- open source code development --
that people own their comments.</p>

<p>I seriously considered Disqus, and I appreciate the engineering work behind it.
It solves a hard problem. I use it to comment on other people's sites. See the
"<a href="#javascriptnotrequiredinbrowser">JavaScript not required</a>" section for why I
ended up not using it. I may reconsider if there is a way to just have a
"comment here" link that would open a Disqus thread either in a new window/fresh
page load. Something where I can just encode some ID in a link to Disqus, but
not need to include any JavaScript in a post to enable comments.</p>

<p>If I want to receive comments on a post, I generate a GitHub Issue for
the post, and then use that URL in a "comments" link in the post.</p>

<p>This works out for me, at least for now, since I use GitHub and most of my posts
are related to code. I appreciate this is not a general purpose commenting
solution.</p>

<h2 id="implementation">Implementation</h2>

<p>I wrote a <a href="http://nodejs.org/">Node-based</a> tool called
<a href="https://github.com/jrburke/delposto">delposto</a>. It does not do much, and I
do not suggest others use it. It is a tool for me, based on my idiosyncracies. Feel free to
open tickets and do pull requests, but set your expectations very low. I am not very motivated to improve it beyond what I need.</p>

<p>The basic idea: write a post in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>,
use <a href="https://github.com/coreyti/showdown">Showdown</a> to convert to HTML, and
apply <a href="https://github.com/janl/mustache.js">Mustache</a> templates to generate
the final static content.</p>

<p>The results should be deployable to <a href="http://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>, particularly if you use
<a href="https://github.com/volojs/volo-ghdeploy">volo-ghdeploy</a>. For this site,
I have an existing hosting account and I just upload the content to that
hosting account.</p>

<p>For the code samples, I use <a href="http://prismjs.com/">Prism</a>. For fonts, I use
<a href="https://typekit.com/">TypeKit</a>.</p>

<p>The "source" for this blog is on GitHub at
<a href="https://github.com/jrburke/jrburke.com">jrburke/jrburke.com</a>.</p>

<p>Any of this could change later, but that is how it works today.</p>]]></content>
    </entry>

</feed>
